A Guide to the Frederick W. Knipe collection FA029
Rockefeller Archive Center
Frederick W. Knipe collection
1930-1951
Rockefeller Archive Center
Knipe, Frederick W.
Rockefeller Foundation
FA029
15 Cubic Feet 17 reels of film and photographs. 15 cubic feet is just a placeholder until extent can be determined.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Frederick W. Knipe deposited his collection with the Rockefeller Foundation Archives in June 1969.
Scope and Contents
Important subjects in this collection include: malaria control, drainage of mosquito breeding, development and use of spraying equipment for insecticides.
Biographical / Historical
Frederick W. Knipe was born in 1893 in Hughesville, Pennsylvania. Attending Penn State from 1913-1917 and Iowa State College from 1919-1920, he studied agricultural engineering and secured a license as a drainage and irrigation engineer. From 1920-1930, Mr. Knipe was Assistant Professor of Engineering at Connecticut Agricultural College and Consulting Engineer for the Raymond Keeler Contracting Company.
Joining the International Health Division in 1930, Mr. Knipe took part in the Rockefeller Foundation's anti-malaria campaigns. From 1930-1937, he worked in Bulgaria and Albania. Transferred to Madras State, India in 1937, he participated in the first area-wide campaigns using insecticide effectively against the adult female mosquito. He remained in India until 1942, when he was attached to the U. S. Army malaria control project in Florida. In Rome in 1944, he served as advisor on malaria control for the Army of Occupation; he then joined the Sardinian Project in 1946. Mr. Knipe was assigned to the Malaria Institute of India in 1952, where he taught the use of equipment for malaria control. He retired from the Rockefeller Foundation in 1958.
A major professional interest of Mr. Knipe's had always been an efficient and effective sprayer for the insecticide. While in Italy he designed and built sprayers and then in India worked on perfecting a portable sprayer. There they made their own equipment to manufacture the insecticide, made their own sprayers, and assembled their own power equipment to activate the sprayers.
Arrangement
Arranged in 2 series:
Series 1021: Photographs.
Series 2: Audiovisual materials.
Insecticides; DDT (Insecticide); Technology; Public health; Malaria
- Frederick W. Knipe Photographs, 1924-1951; 1021; 0.1 Cubic Feet; Approximately 100 prints
  File Plan
  P/1021
  Photographs
  - Durazzo Lagoon Salinification, Albania, 38 prints (Box 7, Folder 67)
    Scope and Contents
    Lagoons, canals, construction.
  - Durazzo Lagoon Salinification, Albania, 1930s; 21 prints (Box 7, Folder 68)
    Lagoons, bridges, construction, canals.
  - Tirana River Project, Albania, 42 prints (Box 7, Folder 69)
    Canals, irrigation, agriculture, dams, construction.
- Frederick W. Knipe Audiovisual materials, 1930-1951; 2
  Biographical / Historical
  Frederick Knipe was a staff member of the International Health Division of the Rockefeller Foundation.
  Arrangement
  Alphabetically.
  The RAC has several silent films from the 1930s about the Tirana River Project in Albania and the efforts to combat malaria throughout the Balkans and in India.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research. When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  All inquiries to view films require advanced notice of at least 2 business days, and may necessitate notice of up to one week. Individual items, including those that are not available in modern formats, may be restricted at the discretion of RAC.
  Moving Images
  - Albania: Durazzo, Tirana, 1930-1937; Silent, Black and white, 10 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 806)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
    Scope and Contents note
    Footage from malaria efforts in Albania (1930-1937), Durazzo (1930-1932), and Tirana (1933-1935). Scenes of drainage project, salinification of lagoon, killing mosquitoes with salt, Dr. Lewis Hackett, Knipe opening a dike.
  - Albania: Porto Romano, 1932; Silent, Black and white, 10 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 807)
    1932 footage of the lagoon in Porto Romano: automatic tide gates, canal entrance; also the lab and headquarters at Tirana.
  - Albania: Shokoset, Tirana, Silent, Black and white, 10 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 808)
    Footage of canal construction and usage.
  - Albania: Tirana - Part I, Silent, Black and white, 10 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 809)
    Tirana River Project: footage of Isuurush Canal and Siphon Dam on the Llana River.
  - Albania: Tirana - Part II, Silent, Black and white, 10 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 810)
    Tirana River Project: Dr. Russell and Dr. G.K. Strode opening the canal and the Calco irrigation gate, the first in Albania.
  - Albania: Tirana - Part III, Silent, Black and white, 10 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 811)
    Tirana River Project: finishing construction of the dam and scenes of the dam in action during a flood.
  - Bulgaria: Ezernitza - Part I, circa 1930; Silent, Black and white, 15 minutes 30 seconds; 16mm film (Reel AV 803)
    Access copy available.
    Footage of the countryside, market day, Romanis dancing at Petrich, washing at a hot water spring, a canal; Dr. Ralph Collins measuring water.
  - Bulgaria: Ezernitza - Part II, 1930; Silent, Black and white, 15 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 804)
    1930 footage of the main canal being inspected by Knipe and Dr. G.K. Strode.
  - Bulgaria: Ezernitza - Part III, circa 1930; Silent, Black and white, 15 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 805)
    Scenes in Luka and Topolnitza: irrigating for corn, building dams, sickling hay.
  - India: Madras - Part I, Silent, Color, 11 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 817)
    Footage of canal construction in Madras State (now Tamil Nadu): mixing plaster by foot, removing earth and stumps; dedication of the Pattukkottai scheme by Dr. Rojan.
  - India: Madras - Part II, Silent, Color, 15 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 818)
    Footage of efforts to kill mosquitoes; pyrethrum spray gun, spraying village houses and rice nurseries.
  - India: Madras - Part III, Silent, Color, 14 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 820)
    Typical scene of mosquito treatments; footage of Sukkur Barrage, largest in India.
  - Malaria War Areas, 1942-1944; Silent, Color, 12 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 816)
    1942-1944 officer training film from World War II: draining mosquito breeding areas, ditch blasting, stumpage.
  - Sardinia, 1930-1932; Silent, Color, 11 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 813)
    1930-1932 footage from tour of Sardinia for group, including Dr. Rollo Hill, Lewis Hackett, Dr. Wilson G. Smillie, and Fred Knipe. Siniscola tour, IHD conference, visit to Sorrento, Italy. Also includes Dr. F.F. Russell, Dr. Rollo Hill, Dr. Marshall Balfour, Dr. Ralph Collins, Dr. Elizabeth Crowell, and engineer Dan Wright.
  - Sardinia: Erlass Project - Part I, Silent, Color, 11 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 812)
    Introduction to Sardinia: footage of villages, coastline, aqueduct ceremony, water wheel powered by a donkey, local life.
  - Sardinia: Erlass Project - Part II, Silent, Color, 11 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 814)
    Footage of the Oliena district, explosives used on drainage projects, clearing riverbeds, curing tobacco, construction on canals.
  - Sardinia Erlass - Part III, Silent, Color, 11 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 815)
    Footage of efforts against malaria: insecticide development in factories, spraying with helicopters, burning dry vegetation to reveal breeding areas.